<?xml version = "1.0" encoding = "utf-8" ?>

<BinaryCommandRunner>

    <class name = "BinaryCommandRunner">

        <main>

            <summary>Runs the command and binds binary CliWrap output and error streams to <see cref="BinaryCommandObserver"/> callbacks.</summary>

        </main>

        <field name = "observer" Cref = "BinaryCommandObserver">

            <summary>Binary Command Observer used to receive notifications and data.</summary>

        </field>

        <field name = "buffered" Cref = "Boolean">

            <summary>Indicates whether RunAsync will return a <see cref="BinaryCommandResult"/> with binary output buffers.</summary>

        </field>

        <field name = "StdOutPipe" Cref = "Pipe">

            <summary>Pipe that receives standard output bytes from the CliWrap command.</summary>

        </field>

        <field name = "StdErrPipe" Cref = "Pipe">

            <summary>Pipe that receives standard error bytes from the CliWrap command.</summary>

        </field>

        <field name = "StdOut" Cref = "Stream">

            <summary>Stream view over the StdOutPipe reader, passed to the BinaryCommandObserver and used for buffering.</summary>

        </field>

        <field name = "StdErr" Cref = "Stream">

            <summary>Stream view over the StdErrPipe reader, passed to the BinaryCommandObserver and used for buffering.</summary>

        </field>

        <constructor name = "Constructor">

            <summary>Initializes a new BinaryCommandRunner with the specified observer and buffering behavior.</summary>

            <param name = "observer" Cref = "BinaryCommandObserver">Binary Command Observer.</param>

            <param name = "buffered" Cref = "Boolean">True to return a <see cref="BinaryCommandResult"/> with binary output; false to stream output to the observer.</param>

            <returns Cref = "BinaryCommandRunner">New BinaryCommandRunner.</returns>

        </constructor>

        <method name = "CreateStdOutTarget">

            <summary>Creates a PipeTarget that copies standard output bytes into the StdOutPipe.</summary>

            <returns Cref = "PipeTarget">PipeTarget that writes stdout into the pipe.</returns>

        </method>

        <method name = "CreateStdErrTarget">

            <summary>Creates a PipeTarget that copies standard error bytes into the StdErrPipe.</summary>

            <returns Cref = "PipeTarget">PipeTarget that writes stderr into the pipe.</returns>

        </method>

        <method name = "RunAsync">

            <summary>Runs the specified CliWrap command, wiring its output and error streams into the observer and returning the final result.</summary>

            <param name = "command" Cref = "CliWrap.Command">CliWrap command to execute.</param>

            <param name = "ct" Cref = "CancellationToken">Forceful cancellation token for the command.</param>

            <param name = "gt" Cref = "CancellationToken">Graceful cancellation token for the command.</param>

            <returns Cref = "Task{CommandResult?}">Task that produces a <see cref="CommandResult"/> when the command and observer processing have completed.</returns>

        </method>

        <method name = "CreateBufferedResultAsync">

            <summary>Creates a <see cref="BinaryCommandResult"/> by reading all remaining data from the stdout and stderr streams.</summary>

            <param name = "baseresult" Cref = "CommandResult">Base command result to augment with binary output.</param>

            <param name = "cancel" Cref = "CancellationToken">Cancellation token used when reading the streams.</param>

            <returns Cref = "Task{BinaryCommandResult}">Task producing the buffered binary command result.</returns>

        </method>

    </class>

</BinaryCommandRunner>